a cardinal error is to try to expand a
culture
linearly like at the same level language
is a good example
so a cardinal error is to say we need
everybody to speak
english or chinese right you pick pick a
language
and so of course as it happens you end
up with an imperial mode right
there's a your mind has to be operating
this particular culture this language
um and now we're competing for minds and
maybe you might speak three languages
but the end of the day this would be
like a finite uh
it's a rivalrous game for mine right in
culture space
if you run it at the meta protocol what
happens is is that
as long as there's a way for us to
establish
in languages is there translatability
communication
can occur and that communication can
occur within certain boundary conditions
i.e that it doesn't
it's not so expensive that it's not
really communication right the entropy
is low enough
then um you you actually you
you you get around the rivalries dynamic
that's like okay great you can have an
arbitrarily large number of cultures
everybody can kind of and if i want to
create my own i can create my own
as long as it's compatible with the meta
protocol i got a lot of room to maneuver
um and and the meta protocols which is
funny about is the meta protocol
is almost geometric what i mean by that
is
you're always going to want to design
your your culture
using the meta protocol because it's
just the best way to design a culture
right if you design a culture outside of
the boundary the meta protocol it's not
like
uh how do i say this
it's like trying to say okay i'm going
to design a body but i'm going to design
a body that can't digest or that dies
within three days you're like that's
kind of a shitty body you could do it
what's the point of that like no no
here's a series of basic rules that that
make
a body work and you know you could
your body can be six foot four it could
be five foot eight you know your skin
color can vary in these directions you
know your eyes like there's a whole
bunch of variation on the morphology
of phylogenetics um but
uh and by the way there's actually wide
varies but a body without a heart is
kind of a non-starter like that's just a
bad idea
so it's kind of like that like the meta
protocols for any violet for any viable
culture that plugs into this
environment um is like a body and so
you've got lots of variations and in
some sense
the there's now no competition because
you're really just looking at
cool explorations of what the
possibility space is inside
the meta protocol which would
potentially be enormous like much larger
than that
than our current space basically
cultures but they're all viable
and part of viability is they're all
interoperable yeah
yeah and they can all interconnect um
and
potentially speak that same language
right on a completely different new
paradigm
ideally which doesn't lead to all the
current
issues that we face um that could
potentially blow
us all up right with the technology
coming up and
yeah yeah that's really interesting i
just i just had some insights on
how to articulate that clearly
um okay so please continue yeah because
that's that's like sorry
i think the constraints are um
if you use the metaphor of speciation at
the body level
there's some value there the point of
speciate or the way we
have come to define speciation is
precisely
lack of compatibility at the genotype
level
and so if i have two phenotypes that
actually
they may be bizarrely compatible like
they can actually mate
in terms of of uh
physicality but they're not compatible
at the genetic level then i don't
actually i have
now two species and what happens of
course is that they
they stop mating and they begin to
species differentiate
exactly um and so the so so the
some of the better questions are like
whoa okay what are the what are the
constraints
and we're finding we're thinking about
in terms of uh
uh peter lindberg's you know cultural
war 2.0 right
um when two
cultures are in a circumstance where the
only way they can be in relationship
with each other
is in fact violence exactly
then they're they're effectively
engaging in a speciation they're now
they're mutually incompatible and
they're engaged in per se rivalrous
competition
um so it's interesting to say okay the
meta protocol effectively is the inverse
of that what's
what's what's a mechanism what are the
characteristics that your
culture must maintain at all times to
ensure
that there's always a non-violent way of
being in relationship with any other
uh culture sorry so please continue well
i mean
sorry what i got from there is you know
how you talked about
the level of change needs to be on the
we create a new dna rna
thing that now opens up that's what i'm
hearing right like
the meta protocol ends up being we have
to figure out what that dna
that allows for all these potential new
cultures to come arise
that are on a different operating system
than what we currently
have yeah and what's interesting is that
it's um
i had this insight yesterday actually it
will be
there will be a lot of resonance with
with
in some sense like the highest tone of
almost all existing cultures
there's a there's a if you
yeah if you use the metaphor of um like
the emergence of the of the neuron of
neurology
like okay there's a like the
proto-neuron like the the proto-retinol
the proto-photosensitive cell
there's a a movement where
there's a cell that has a certain
sensitivity to photon um
but it's kind of haphazard it's sort of
not
it's not useful enough to really build
stuff you can't build eyeballs with it
right it's just not high fidelity enough
it's not consistent enough it's not
repeatable enough but
if you kind of look at the there's like
a a vector
that is pointing towards this this place
this location is like okay now that
is the thing right and if i see the
the tree like the series of of uh you
know evolutionary stages i can i can
actually see where they are on the arrow
and the ones that are closest to the
final to the to the actual point
like oh i've got now got a a a retinal
cell like a photocell
or a photosensitive cell like the ones
that are just prior to that
this i'm anthropomorphizing the ones
that are just prior to that i'd be like
yes
that that's what i was trying to get to
[Music]
and even though they may all be
variations the commonality is that
they're all going to point at that right
so there's like
the highest tone the highest yearning
the thing that has been the most
noble or valorous aspect of many many
different cultures
is the point i guess that's the vector
we can kind of suss out that vector
and say oh okay that's the noble the
noble the noble thing that's been trying
to arise
in culture we've now we can now kind of
point at it and now
many many different cultures will be
able to look at this new thing and say
oh yeah yeah
yeah cool that's that's that's it that's
kind of
reified the good part in like an
alchemical essence we captured
the part that we've been trying to get
to the essence just
trying to express itself and have been
able to to get rid of the stuff that was
you know legacy that needs to go away
the michelangelo move yeah the
michelangelo move